So again just to review we're here on יג עמוד א Yud
Gimmel Amud Alef and we have that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
that the student said in the name of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael
that they did not debate בית הלל Bais Hillel and בית שמאי
Bais Shammai less than four אמות Amot and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says no רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael never said such a thing but
then he says but we rule like that student. The גמרא Gemara
says how could he literally rule like that student but he was
doing it in order to provoke the other students to see what
their response would be. Now the question is is that what does
it mean that he said it that we rule like the student?
It doesn't matter because the student just said or this position in
the name of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael just said that less than
four אמות Amot בית הלל Bais Hillel and בית שמאי Bais Shammai
agree לחי Lechi or a קורה. Korah. But anyway we rule like
בית הלל. Bais Hillel. So if we rule like בית הלל Bais
Hillel לחי Lechi or a קורה Korah up to ten אמות Amot
what difference does it make if they debated less than four אמות?
Amot? Right? You understand the point regardless of whether the גמרא's Gemara's
only concern was did רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva really say the הלכה
Halacha was like that student. But it's a moot point because בית
הלל Bais Hillel says לחי Lechi or a קורה Korah and the
only question is did בית שמאי Bais Shammai agree to בית הלל
Bais Hillel less than four אמות. Amot. But we rule like בית
הלל Bais Hillel anyway so it's really pretty much a moot point.
So someone is saying no the relevance of saying we if we
were to rule that less than four אמות Amot would make a
difference then it would have other implications. So if less than four
אמות Amot by a מבוי Mavoi בית שמאי Bais Shammai would agree
to בית הלל Bais Hillel that could mean for example that less
than four אמות Amot by a חצר Chatzer maybe also would require
less. So yesterday we said a חצר Chatzer required a פס Pas
on either side or a four טפח Tefach פס Pas but if
we're going to admit that less than four אמות Amot makes a
difference maybe it would have implications for us even in other cases
like maybe less than four אמות Amot in a חצר Chatzer would
be less. So anyway that's why there might actually be a relevant
halachic implication of ruling that way but the גמרא Gemara says again
that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva insists רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael never said
such a thing and even though he said we rule like that
תלמיד Talmid who said less than four אמות Amot is not a
debate he only did it to sharpen the students. Okay. Now the
גמרא Gemara continues אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi about eight lines from the top יג עמוד א. Yud Gimmel
Amud Alef. Said רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi כל
מקום שאתה מוצא משום רבי ישמעאל אמר תלמיד אחד לפני רבי עקיבא
Kol makom she'ata motzei mishum Rabbi Ishmael amar talmud echad lifnei Rabbi
Akiva anytime you say this that a student said in front of
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in the name of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael
now how often we have that I don't know I didn't check
but whenever you find that phrase a certain student said in the
name of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael in the presence of רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva אינו אלא רבי מאיר Eino ela Rabbi Meir that student
who was getting the teaching of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael and reporting
it to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva must be רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
ששימש את רבי ישמעאל ואת רבי עקיבא She-shimesh et Rabbi Ishmael ve-et
Rabbi Akiva because we know he basically attended to meaning studied both
from רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva which is
pretty interesting like was he the only student that was the crossover
but somehow the גמרא Gemara thinks that he was the only prominent
student and therefore if a student is reporting רבי ישמעאל's Rabbi Ishmael's
words to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva it must be רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir דתניא De-tanya we taught in the ברייתא Braisa and now we're
going to get into a little interesting biography or whatever story about
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir studying both from רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael and
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
אמר רבי מאיר Amar Rabbi Meir said רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir כשהייתי
אצל רבי ישמעאל Keshe-hayiti etzel Rabbi Ishmael when I was learning by
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael הייתי מטיל קנקנתום לתוך הדיו Hayiti matil kankantom
le-toch ha-deyo I would put קנקנתום Kankantom into the דיו. Deyo. קנקנתום
Kankantom is a debate of רש"י Rashi tells us what it means
according to Steinsaltz it's copper sulfate and we will see from the
story that what it does is it makes the ink more permanent
it makes it harder to scrape away and erase.
Yes רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was a סופר Sofer and we're going
to see that in a minute he actually made a profession as
a סופר. Sofer. ולא אמר לי דבר Velo amar li davar and
he didn't comment he didn't respond he saw me do it he
didn't say anything. כשבאתי אצל רבי עקיבא Keshe-bati etzel Rabbi Akiva when
I came to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva to learn with him אסרה
עלי Asarah alai he forbade it to me. Anyway the relevance of
that for us is that we see that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
learned from both רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
Now the גמרא's Gemara's going to question this
איני Eini is this really true that that's what happened?
והאמר רבי יהודה אמר שמואל משום רבי מאיר Ve-ha-amar Rabbi Yehuda amar
Shmuel mishum Rabbi Meir but we have a tradition in the name
of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in the name of שמואל Shmuel in
the name of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that has the version a
little bit different. כשהייתי לומד אצל רבי עקיבא Keshe-hayiti lomed etzel Rabbi
Akiva
it starts with learning under רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva when I was
learning by רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva הייתי מטיל קנקנתום לתוך הדיו Hayiti
matil kankantom le-toch ha-deyo I would put this קנקנתום Kankantom into the
דיו Deyo ולא אמר לי דבר Velo amar li davar and
he didn't respond. וכשבאתי אצל רבי ישמעאל U-cheshe-bati etzel Rabbi Ishmael and
when I came to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael אמר לי Amar li
he said to me בני מה מלאכתך Beni ma melachtecha my son
what is your what's your profession? אמרתי לו Amarti lo I said
to him לבלר אני Lavlari ani I am a scribe. אמר לי
Amar li he said to me בני הוי זהיר במלאכתך Beni hevei
zahir bimlachtecha my son be very careful in your you know in
your profession in your work שמלאכתך מלאכת שמים היא She-melachtecha melachet shamayim
hi it's heavenly work that you're writing ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah היא
hi שמא אתה מחסר אות אחת Shema ata mechasser ot achat
and you have to be very careful because if you just for
example you know lack drop off one letter או מיתר אות אחת
O meyater ot achat or have one extra letter נמצאת מחריב את
כל העולם כולו Nimtset machriv et kol ha'olam kulo you'll destroy the
entire world. Now how will you destroy the entire world? So רש"י
Rashi and תוספות Tosfos both discuss what letter could be so disastrous.
תוספות Tosfos speaks about if you said בראשית ברא אלקים Bereishis bara
Elokim and instead of ברא bara you did בראשית בראו, Bereishis bra-u,
so maybe God you know had somehow been created or something.
Now anyway, right,
anyway רש"י Rashi says that if the פסוק pasuk is והשם אלקים
אמת, v’Hashem Elokim emes, if you didn’t have the אלף aleph then
אמת emes would become מת. meis.
So that would be pretty disastrous.
Or if you said וידבר השם, v’yidabeir Hashem, if you made it
an added a ו vov and did וידברו. v’yidbru. So things that
would be very heretical obviously to say. The מהרש"א Maharsha quoting, he
doesn’t say he’s quoting the רמב"ן, Ramban, but he’s quoting the רמב"ן,
Ramban, the kabbalistic idea that all of the letters of the תורה
Torah basically are, you know, form a, you know, an elongated word
of a name of God. And you know, and that every single
letter has a, the sort of mystical power in terms of the
תורה Torah and their arrangement. So one letter just changes that whole,
you know, that whole metaphysical reality created by the words of the
תורה. Torah. So anyway, but clearly that it is extremely, extremely
significant every single letter you do and you have to be so
scrupulous about this. Now, it is worth noting that in the time
of חז"ל, Chazal, there was more variance in terms of the exact,
you know, תורה Torah script. I don’t mean like major things, but
I mean like if a word is מלא malei or חסר, chaser,
you know, some of these types of smaller issues was greater variance.
You know, it was the work of the מסורת masores
which were, which were you know, counted every single letter and categorized
it all, which leads to the high degree of standardization that we
currently have in our ספרי תורה. Sifrei Torah. So that's number one
anyway, the possibility of מחסר mechasser or מיתר, miyater, but presumably if
it was within the normal variance, then there's nothing you can do
if there are those variants. But anyway, it does give I think
an extra punch to why you know it's so important to be
as careful as you can,
especially if maybe you're at a time when there is not as
much standardization, how much more so could that lead to being perhaps
a little sloppy and the emphasis of being careful. Another interesting position
here or insight is given by the מהרי"ץ חיות. Maharitz Chayes. And
he says that, a like a 19th-century scholar, he says that we
know as רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that he was a scribe.
We also know not only was he a scribe, but that he
often did דרשות drashos on the פסוקים psukim almost by like playing
with the letters. Like a famous one is where it says כתנות
עור kasnos or that God made for אדם וחווה Adam v’Chava garments
of leather, he read as כתנות אור kasnos or with an אלף,
aleph, like out of light.
רש"י, Rashi, right,
and there are other types of דרשות drashos that he did. So
apparently the concern was or so I can say what he did
was he might have written in the margin of his ספר תורה
Sefer Torah some of his like little דרשות. drashos. Like about on
that פסוק pasuk or רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Now some are a
little shocked by this. How, he would write something in the margin
of a ספר תורה? Sefer Torah? But maybe he would write like
maybe put like a dot or some type of a thing to,
you know, as a symbol to him of his like דרשה drasha
on the פסוק. pasuk. And that could be why רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael was particularly, this is not my ווארט, vort, this is the
מהרי"ץ חיות Maharitz Chayes is a huge תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, whatever,
you know, but also very, you know, more sort of broad in
his thinking. Anyway, he says that that could be why רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael was so anxious. You know, he knew not only that
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was a scribe, but he knew he liked
playing with the פסוקים psukim and doing these types of דרשות. drashos.
And he said, you know, don't get carried away and be very
careful that you don't somehow write your little letter, you know, your
play on words and actually transforms into what you're actually writing in
the script. You know, you have this brilliant idea, so maybe you
write כתנות אור kasnos or with an אלף aleph and you don't
write it with an עין. ayin. So be very careful. Okay, so
that's stage one.
Okay, now it goes
on. אמרתי לו, Amarti lo, so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says I
said back to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, דבר אחד יש לי davar
echad yesh li וקנקנתום שמו. v’kankantum shemo.
By the way, you should be aware I've got this
special additive to my ink which I call קנקנתום, kankantum, which again
may be this copper sulfate, שאני מטילו לתוך הדיו, she’ani matilo l’soch
hadyo, I put it into the ink. I put it into the
ink. אמר לי, Amar li, so he said back to me, וכי
מטילין קנקנתום לתוך הדיו? vechi matilin kankantum l’soch hadyo? Do you think
you're allowed to do that? והלא אמרה תורה, vehalo amra Torah, the
תורה Torah says, וכתב ומחה, v’chasav umacha,
by the book of the סוטה, Sotah, by what you write out
by the סוטה, Sotah, it says you should write it and then
you should scrape it into the water. כתב שיכול להמחות, ksav sheyachol
lehimachos,
so it only it has to be write, so the definition of
writing is something that can be scraped away and erased. And this
קנקנתום kankantum makes it impossible to erase. So we'll get back and
analyze that issue of the problem of קנקנתום kankantum in a minute.
But first the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי קאמר ליה ומאי
קא מהדר ליה? mai ka amar lei u’mai ka mehadar lei? I
don't get it. How was what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said responsive
to what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said to him? רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael said be very careful not to write extra letters or fewer
letters, and he said, oh, by the way, I've got this great
little additive I put in my ink. What's the relevance? So he
said what, can't erase it? Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say. So it says, הכי קאמר ליה. hachi ka amar
lei. So here's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was, said back to
רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. לא מיבעיא בחסירות וביתירות דלא טעיתי. lo mibaya
b’chasiros u’v’yesiros d’lo ta-isi. You don't have to worry, Rabbi Yishmael. Not
only do I not make mistakes of writing, taking away a letter
or adding a letter, דבקי אנא. De'baki ana. I know I'm an
expert at the script and at the letters and I don't make
that mistake at all. Don't worry about that. אלא, Ella, but you
know what? I want to tell you how good I am. Not
only do I not make those mistakes, אפילו מחשלא דזבוב נמי דלמא
אתי ויתיב אתאגא דדלת ומחיק ליה ומשוי ליה ריש, afilu michshla d'z'vuv
nami delma ati v'yasiv atage d'dalet umachei lei umashvei lei reish, that
you don't even have to worry. I am even concerned about, not
only that I'll write an extra letter or take away a letter,
I'm concerned, I am so scrupulous, I'm concerned that maybe a fly
will land on the script as the ink is drying and he'll
take and he'll sit on the little protrusion of the דלת, dalet,
you know where the דלת dalet goes off to the right, the
top of the דלת, dalet, to the right of the bar underneath,
and then he'll erase it and then the דלת dalet would become
a ריש. reish. Don't worry. I am so super careful, I put
something into my ink to make sure that even accidental erasures don't
occur. דבר
אחד יש לי. Davar echad yesh li. You should be aware that
I'm so, that what I do is I put this special additive
in, קנקנתום שמו שאני מטיל לתוך הדיו. Kankantom shemo she'ani matil l'toch
had'yo. Okay, so that was why he was responding, how it was
relevant to this issue of חסירות ויתירות. chasirot v'yiteirot. But now we've
got a problem. Did he learn, the first version is he learned
by Rabbi Yishmael and then he didn't say anything and he went
to Rabbi Akiva who said something. This version is that he went
to Rabbi, he started with Rabbi Akiva who didn't say anything and
then he went to Rabbi Yishmael and Rabbi Yishmael had the reaction.
So which is it? And the גמרא's Gemara going to get back
to that. So the גמרא Gemara says קשיא שימוש אשימוש קשיא עשייה
אעשייה. Kashya shimush a-shimush kashya asiya a-asiya. We have a contradiction. First
of all, who did he attend to first, Rabbi Yishmael or Rabbi
Akiva? And number two, who was the one who said it was
forbidden? According to the first version it was Rabbi Akiva who said
it after he left Rabbi Yishmael. According to the second version it
was Rabbi Yishmael who said it after he left Rabbi Akiva. So
the גמרא Gemara says בשלמא שימוש אשימוש לא קשיא. Bishlama shimush a-shimush
lo kashya. That's just the question of who did he attend to,
who did he study from, what order he did it. That's not
a problem because we can reconcile that. מעיקרא אתא לקמיה דרבי עקיבא.
Me'ikara ata l'kamei d'Rabbi Akiva. We could say he started with Rabbi
Akiva, ומדלא
מצי למיקם אליביה, umid'lo matzi l'meikav al libei, he wasn't able
to really fully get what Rabbi Akiva was teaching, to understand literally
to understand his heart. He couldn't, Rabbi Akiva taught his teaching and
it was above Rabbi Meir's head. He wasn't at the level that
he could understand it. אזל לקמיה דרבי ישמעאל. Azal l'kamei d'Rabbi Yishmael.
So then he went over to Rabbi Yishmael, וגמר גמרא, v'gmar g'mara,
and he learned the tradition. Meaning וגמר גמרא v'gmar g'mara is not
yet the סברא. svara. Well yeah, but it doesn't mean he learned
how to learn. What it means is like he learned all of
the material. He learned all the whole tradition. גמר גמרא Gmar g'mara
is more like just downloading or uploading, like it's just receiving everything
that somebody has to teach. So he learned the entire oral tradition.
Remember there were no books so you had to just learn the
material. והדר, V'hadar, now that he knew the
material, הדר אתא לקמיה דרבי עקיבא וסבר סברא. hadar ata l'kamei d'Rabbi
Akiva v'savar svara. Then he went to Rabbi Akiva and he was
able to learn analytic ability and he was able to understand Rabbi
Akiva's more
incisive
analysis. Which is by the way an important issue, because the גמרא
Gemara has a question, is it more important like the famous גמרא
Gemara asks, is it more important to be like
סיני או עוקר הרים? Sinai o oker harim? סיני Sinai is like
you got the Torah from הר סיני, Har Sinai, you know all
the material, and עוקר הרים oker harim like you can lift up
the mountain means that you can analyze it and you can break
it down and so on. And which is more important? And the
גמרא Gemara has that whole debate. Anyway, and certainly at one stage
without looking at that גמרא Gemara exactly, the idea how good can
you be as an עוקר הרים oker harim if you're not yet
a סיני? Sinai? What good is your analysis if you don't have
enough material to look at and you don't have all the information
and you can't bring all the relevant information into the conversation? So
what the גמרא Gemara is saying is it's not that Rabbi Meir
was not able to, didn't have the intellect to get what Rabbi
Akiva was doing. He just hadn't learned enough information. He hadn't learned
enough of the tradition. Once he had received all of the tradition
from Rabbi Yishmael, then he was able to be the proper student
of Rabbi Akiva. Anyway, so that's how we learned and we're going
to go back to that also the whole question about Rabbi Meir's
intellect. But right now anyway that's how we've reconciled who did he
learn from, which order did he do it. He actually says he
went back and forth. Okay, but now how about the other problem?
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא עשייה אעשייה קשיא. Ella asiya a-asiya
kashya. We've got a problem. Who is the one that said it
was forbidden? Was it Rabbi Akiva or Rabbi Yishmael? The גמרא Gemara
says קשיא. Kashya. You're right, that is a problem. We have different
versions of who was the one that said it was forbidden
and we cannot reconcile that. Now just to remind you the whole
point of quoting this whole story was to prove that the student
who reported Rabbi Yishmael's teaching to Rabbi Akiva must have been Rabbi
Meir because he is the one student we know that transferred over
from Rabbi Yishmael to Rabbi Akiva. Okay, now that we're talking about
this issue about scraping and can you use this קנקנתום, kankantom, we'll
continue with that. תני תנא ברייתא, Tani tana baraita, רבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי מאיר היה אומר. Rabbi Meir haya omer. Rabbi
Yehuda says Rabbi Meir used to say לכל מטילין קנקנתום לתוך הדיו
חוץ מפרשת סוטה. L'chol matilin kankantom l'toch had'yo chutz mi'parshat sota. So
maybe he didn't accept what Rabbi Yishmael said or maybe this is
what Rabbi Yishmael meant. You can put this קנקנתום kankantom, *kankantom* into
the ink for all purposes except for writing the פרשה *parsha* of
the סוטה Sota *Sotah*. Because the סוטה Sota. *Sotah*, there the קנקנתום
*kankantom* is a problem, it has to be able to be scraped
away. Now what was רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael* saying when
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael* objected in general? So some say
even רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael. *Rabbi Yishmael* was only objecting to using
it for the פרשת סוטה Sota *parshat sotah*, not for the rest
in the תורה Torah *Torah*, not for the rest... yes, well that
clearly he couldn't do, not for the rest of the ספר תורה
Sefer Torah, *Sefer Torah*, just for פרשת סוטה Sota *parshat sotah*. And
as we'll see in a minute because there are opinions that you
might that you could use the פרשת סוטה Sota *parshat sotah* in
the ספר תורה Sefer Torah, *Sefer Torah* for a סוטה Sota *Sotah*.
So רבי Rabbi, ישמעאל'ס *Rabbi Yishmael's* objection really was not about הלכות
ספר תורה Sefer Torah, *hilchos Sefer Torah*, that maybe wouldn't be a
problem maybe even in פרשת סוטה Sota *parshat sotah*, his objection was
you shouldn't be using it because you might want because it's important
for פרשת סוטה Sota *parshat sotah* and not be used for the
sake of סוטה Sota. *Sotah*. Of course at the time of רבי
Rebbi ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* they weren't doing סוטה Sota *Sotah* anymore. Anyway,
that's one way of reading it that what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*Rabbi Meir* said here is exactly the only thing that רבי ישמעאל
*Rabbi Yishmael* meant. It doesn't sound like that. It sounds like רבי
ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* had a broader objection about not using it for
any part of the ספר תורה Torah *Sefer Torah*. And the question
is why. So if you take a look at this תוספות Tosafos
*Tosafot*, חוץ מפרשת סוטה Sota, *chutz miparshes sotah*, תוספות *Tosafot* says the
following. אמר רבי Amar Rabbi, ישמעאל שהיה אוסר בכל התורה כולה *Amar
Rabbi Yishmael shehaya oser bechol haTorah kullah*, שמא היה דורש גזירה שוה
מסוטה *shema haya doresh gezeira shava misotah*. Maybe he said like because
he said וכתב ומחה *vechasav umacha*, כתב *ksav* has to be writing
that can be erased. So maybe he felt that if that's true
about פרשת סוטה *parshat sotah* it's true about everything. Any type of
writing is only halachic writing if it can be erased. וכתב וכתב
*Vechasav vechasav*, you know, maybe from the word כתב *ksav*, או גזירה
שוה אחרת *o gezeira shava acheres*, maybe some other גזירה שוה *gezeira
shava*. אי נמי מדרבנן *Ee nami midrabbanan*, maybe it was rabbinic. Since
a סוטה *Sotah* can't you have to can't use it, you can't
use it in the rest of the ספר תורה Torah. *Sefer Torah*.
So it's an interesting question. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* limited
the problem just to פרשת סוטה *parshat sotah*, but it's a question
רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* might have seen it as much broader. Okay,
so that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says. Back to
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
רבי יעקב אומר משמו *Rabbi Yaakov omer mishmo*.
Now רבי יעקב *Rabbi Yaakov* says in the name of רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*. Interesting. So before we had רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir* saying things in the name of רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi
Yishmael* and reporting them. Now we have people reporting רבי מאיר'ס *Rabbi
Meir's* position. So רבי יעקב *Rabbi Yaakov* says in the name of
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir*, חוץ מפרשת סוטה שבמקדש *chutz miparshes
sotah shebamikdash*. No no no. You can use it in פרשת סוטה
*parshat sotah* in the ספר תורה Torah. *Sefer Torah*. You just can't
use it in the in the actual סוטה *Sotah* scroll you're writing
when you do the procedure in the מקדש *Mikdash*. סו מאי בינייהו
*So mai beinaihu*, what's their debate about? אמר רבי ירמיה למחוק לה
מן התורה איכא בינייהו *Amar Rabbi Yirmiya limchok lah min haTorah eika
beinaihu*. The debate is whether you can use the פרשת סוטה *parshat
sotah* in the ספר תורה Torah *Sefer Torah*. If you can't use
it for סוטה *Sotah*, then no need to to avoid the קנקנתום
*kankantom*. But if you can use it for a סוטה *Sotah*, maybe
you want it always somehow available for that use. It's an interesting
question why you would want it always available for that use but
okay, that's the issue. Can you use the one actually written in
the ספר תורה Torah *Sefer Torah*?
Oh wait, didn't they have it in and wasn't one of the
things that they did later on someone wrote it on on like
on like a gold thing so it would never have to be
erased?
That was הלני *Heleni*?
No, that was so that you would have the script that you
could copy it down. You would have the fixed script so you
could write it down based on it. No, but you have to
write it on קלף *klaf* and erase it. Yeah exactly. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says right right. והני תנאי כי הני תנאי *Vahani
tannai kehani tannai*. So these תנאים Tannaim *Tannaim* about whether you can
use the פרשת סוטה *parshat sotah* in the ספר תורה Torah *Sefer
Torah* is parallels the following debate of תנאים *Tannaim*. דתניא *Detanya*, it
was taught in a ברייתא braita. *braisa*, אין מגילה כשרה להשקות בה
סוטה אחרת *Ein megillah keshera l'hashkos bah sotah acheres*. The מגילה *megillah*
of a כשרה *kshera* is not valid to wash for another סוטה
*Sotah*. If you write it for one סוטה *Sotah* and then let's
say she admits or something else happens, you cannot use it for
another סוטה *Sotah*. רבי אחאי בר יאשיה אומר מגילה כשרה להשקות בה
סוטה אחרת *Rabbi Achai bar Yoshiya omer megillah keshera l'hashkos bah sotah
acheres*. No, there's no idea of לשמה lishma. *lishmah*, you can write
it for one סוטה *Sotah* and use it for another סוטה *Sotah*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says this is a debate of whether
there's an idea of לשמה lishma *lishmah*, it has to be written
for that particular person. And presumably that's the same issue of can
you use the פרשת סוטה *parshat sotah* in a ספר תורה Torah.
*Sefer Torah*? Because it wasn't written for this particular woman. Is that
a requirement for פרשת סוטה *parshat sotah*? So presumably it's the same
debate. So אמר רב פפא *amar Rav Papa* says רב פפא *Rav
Papa*, לאו היא *lav hee*, maybe it's not the same debate. עד
כאן לא קאמר תנא Tana, קמא התם Hasam *Ad kan lo ka'amar
tana kama hatam*, over there the תנא Tana. קמא *tana kama* says
that you can't use it for another woman, אלא כיון דאיתחזק לשם
רחל Rachel, *ela kivan de'itchazak l'shem Rachel*, once it is like set,
you know, pulled away, meaning once it is designated for a particular
woman, for רחל Rachel *Rachel*, תו לא הדר מיתחזי לשם לאה Leah,
*tu lo hadar mitchazi l'shem Leah*, it can no longer be assigned
to לאה Leah *Leah*. So there the problem is that it's written
for a different woman. אבל גבי תורה Aval gabei Torah, *Aval gabi
Torah*, but when it comes to if you can use the one
written in the ספר תורה *Sefer Torah*, דסתמא מיכתבא *distama michtava*, it's
not written for anybody in particular, it's written סתם *stam*, it's written
generically, maybe even with no סוטה *Sotah* in mind, הכי נמי דמחקינן
*hachi nami demachkinan*, maybe you could do it. Meaning maybe nobody requires
positive לשמה lishma *lishmah*, they just require that it not be written
for someone else. And therefore maybe you could write it in the
ספר תורה *Sefer Torah*. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק *Amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak*, so said רב נחמן בר יצחק *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*,
איפכא מסתברא *ipcha mistabra*, I'll give you another way why the debate
might not be relevant. We wanted to say that even the one
that said it doesn't work for רחל Rachel *Rachel* for if you
wrote it for רחל Rachel *Rachel* doesn't work for לאה Leah, *Leah*
would say it works if you write it in the ספר תורה
*Sefer Torah*. I could argue the opposite way. עד כאן לא קאמר
רבי אחאי בר יאשיה התם *Ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Achai bar
Yoshiya hatam*, there where רבי אחאי בר יאשיה *Rabbi Achai bar Yoshiya*
said... It says if you wrote it for רחל Rachel you could
use it for לאה, Leah? maybe that's better than the ספר תורה,
not worse. Why would that be better? אלא דאיכתב מיהת לשום סוטה
בעולם, Ella de'ichtav mi'has l'shum Sota ba'olam, it was at least written
to be used as a סוטה parchment. It was written for the
ritual of the סוטה. So maybe רחל, לאה Leah doesn't matter, but
to be used for a סוטה it has to be written for
that ritual. אבל גבי תורה, but by a תורה דלשמה כתיבה, de'lishma
ktiva, it was done for practice. It doesn't literally mean practice, but
it means it was done with no intent to use it for
the סוטה ritual. הכי נמי דלא מחקנינן, Hachi nami de'lo machkinan,
maybe you couldn't use it. So the גמרא Gemara says it's not
necessarily the same debate. On the one hand, having כוונה kavannah for
a different woman could be worse than having כוונה kavannah for no
woman, generic. Number two, you could say the opposite. Having כוונה, kavannah,
maybe it has to be written for at least for the סוטה
ritual and written totally generically might not be usable. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara says דלית ליה לרבי אחא בר יוסף, de'lais lei l'Rabbi
Akha bar Yosef, now that we're talking about it, רבי אחא בר
יוסף Rabbi Akha bar Yosef that says if you wrote
for רחל you could use it for לאה, Leah. doesn't he hold
הדתנן hada'tnan that which we taught in the משנה, Mishna, כתב גט
לגרש את אשתו, katav get l'garesh es ishto, somebody wrote a גט
get to divorce his wife, top of י"ג עמוד ב', Yud-Gimmel Amud-Beis,
ונמלך ומצאו בן עירו, ve'nimlach u'metzo ben iro, and then
he had a change of heart, maybe I won't divorce her, and
then he bumped into somebody else from his city, it has to
be from his city because the גט get also says what city
you live in, ואמר, ve'amar, and he said שמך כשמי ושם אשתך
כשם אשתי, shimcha kishmi ve'shem ishtecha k'shem ishti,
hey, you're not using that גט get anymore, you have the same
name I do and my wife has the same name your wife
does, maybe I'll let me use that גט get for my wife,
פסול לגרש בו, pasul l'garesh bo, you can't use it. So anyway,
bottom line is, if you wrote for one woman you can't write
for another. A גט get has to be לשמה. lishma And the
גמרא's Gemara assuming that the same requirements of לשמה lishma. that apply
by גט get apply by a מגילת סוטה. Megillat Sota. So how
could the somebody say by סוטה if you wrote it for רחל
you could use it for לאה? What is that idea? So the
obvious answer is that maybe there's no לשמה requirement. There's a specific
לשמה requirement by גט, get, maybe it doesn't exist or maybe it's
of a different nature. So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer
is. הכי השתא? Hachi hashta? How can you compare those cases? התם
דכתב לה
כתיב, de'ktav la ktiv, it says you should write for her, that's
the language of תורה says by a גט, get, בעינן כתיבה לשמה,
beinan ktiva lishma, it needs to be written for her sake. הכא,
Hacha, here, now could just end it here, there's no need for
לשמה. The גמרא Gemara doesn't go that far. It says הכא hacha
ועשה לה כתיב, ve'asa la ktiv, it says the כהן Kohen shall
do for her this entire procedure. It doesn't say you should write
for her, it should do it for her. בעינן עשייה לשמה, beinan
asiya lishma, the doing has to be for her sake. What's the
doing? עשייה דידם מחיקה היא, Asiya didam mchika hi, the key act
for this סוטה is not the writing, the writing is a preparatory
stage, the key act is the scraping into the water. So that
has to be for her. It could be that the actual writing
of the parchment itself does not have to be for this particular
woman. So there could, yes, be a different standard by סוטה
than by what do you call it, than by the גט. get.
Now תוספות says it doesn't mean that there's no requirement by סוטה.
Remember the גמרא Gemara said that it could be that even the
one who says you can use from רחל for לאה would might
say you can't use the one from the ספר תורה, right? So
there maybe there's some minimal requirement that the כתיבה ktiva has to
be for the purpose of סוטה in general, but the specific idea
that for this specific woman that we require by a גט, get,
here we would not require that in the writing. At most we
would require that in the scraping, at least according to this position.
Other position disagrees and says no, if you wrote for רחל you
can't use for לאה. Okay. Now, אמר רבי אחא
בר
חנינא. Amar Rabbi Akha bar Chanina. Now that we're done with showing
how רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was the student of רבי ישמעאל and
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and an interesting story about him being a
scribe and getting this pushback about using this קנקנתום, which in the
end maybe is only a problem by סוטה, maybe not a problem
by ספר תורה, now whatever, now we go on to look at
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir more of a story about רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir, himself, because you know, we had something that maybe would have
raised questions about רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir, intellectual acuity. He didn't get,
he had to go to רבי ישמעאל before he could come back
to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דברי סופרים? Divrei Sofrim? Right. So now
we're going to put any of those questions to rest. Let's take
a look. אמר רבי אחא בר חנינא, Amar Rabbi Akha bar Chanina,
גלוי וידוע לפני מי שאמר והיה העולם, gali v'yadu'a lifnei mi she'amar
ve'haya ha'olam, it is revealed and known in front of the one
who said and the world came into being, meaning before God, שאין
בדורו של רבי מאיר כמותו, she'ein b'doro shel Rabbi Meir kamoso, there
was nobody at the level, the intellectual level of רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir, in his generation. ומפני מה לא קבעו הלכה כמותו? U'mipnei ma
lo kav'u halacha kamoso? So why did we not always rule like
him? Now it's not like we specifically say we rule against רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir. but nevertheless in standard debates רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir.
is the one that loses out. רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir against רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, we rule like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי מאיר,
Rebbe Meir, normally we don't rule like רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir? we
sometimes rule like רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir. but as a general rule
we often rule like others and not like רבי מאיר. Rebbe Meir
That being said, I should point out that the גמרא Gemara says
סתם מתניתין רבי מאיר, stam matnisin Rabbi Meir, that רבי... רבי יהודה
הנשיא, Rebbe Yehuda HaNasi, what he used as the sort of base
of
the משניות mishnayos was the teachings of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir, That
being said, you know, when it's not a סתם משנה stam mishna
and when he's debating, we often rule against him. So if he
was really the smartest of his
generation, why do we not always rule like him? שלא יכלו חבריו
לעמוד על סוף דעתו. Shelo yachlu chaveirav la-amod al sof da'ato. He
was so smart that nobody knew what he was talking about. Okay?
That nobody could fully understand, you know, what his thinking was on
a particular matter. שהוא אומר
על טמא טהור ומראה לו פנים. Shehu omer al tamei tahor u-marei
lo panim. He could say that something that either everybody else assumed
was טמא, tamei, he could say it was טהור tahor and bring
evidence. Or it doesn't just mean everybody else assumes, as we're about
to see in a story, he could even prove about something that
really was טמא. tamei. He was so brilliant, you know, that he
could make a good argument that something that was טמא tamei should
be טהור. tahor. על טהור טמא, Al tahor tamei, and the reverse,
he could say something that clearly was טהור tahor and, you know,
he could quote sources and make an argument that it should be
טמא. tamei. ומראה לו פנים, U-marei lo panim, and he'd be able
to bring evidence to his position. So, which could also mean that
not just they couldn't understand his argument, which it might mean, but
it also maybe could also mean they couldn't trust his arguments. Because,
you know, they said if you're so smart that you can prove
anything, then how do we know that, you know, to trust any
argument—not that he would intentionally misrepresent, but that just like, you know,
if you have the brilliance that you can prove anything, then we,
you know, then for us, then it—then we can't trust that it's
really a good proof because maybe it's just, you know, you've managed
to prove something that we really wouldn't agree with. Yes?
Question: one of the qualifications to be on the סנהדרין Sanhedrin to
be...
Yes, so it is true, the גמרא Gemara does say, the גמרא's
Gemara going to get into that a little bit, that you have
to in general, you have to have that degree of mastery. But
presumably רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir could outdo them all with that. Okay.
Now it is interesting and this is going to raise a question
we're going to get to this a little bit later in today's
דף daf after the debate of בית הלל Beis Hillel בית שמאי,
Beis Shammai, which is, you know, how much do you go by
majority vote and how much do you go by brilliance? And how
much can you if you're ruling, like if I know that you're
so brilliant, you know what, I'll just cast my vote in with
you, yeah, he always knows what he's talking about, I'll just assume
he's right. And presumably that wasn't the case. Presumably for a rabbi
to actually פסקן pasken meant that he himself had to be able
to, you know, be convinced of the logic. He himself had to
understand the reason behind it. You can't just like, you know, sign
over your vote, what's called proxy your vote. So that if you
can't explain it to me in a way that I can really
make sense of it or I can trust the logic, then I
can't give you my vote and I'm going to have to vote
with what makes sense to me. So, so let's see a little
bit more about this and then we can talk a little more.
Okay. תנא, לא רבי מאיר שמו, lo Rebbe Meir shemo, his original
name was not רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, אלא רבי נהוראי שמו. ela
Rebbe Nehorai shemo. It was רבי נהוראי Rebbe Nehorai
was his original name. ולמה נקרא שמו רבי מאיר? Ve-lamah nikra shemo
Rebbe Meir? So why was he called רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir שהיה
מאיר עיני חכמים בהלכה. She-hayah me-ir einei chachamim ba-halacha. Because he would
enlighten the eyes of sages in הלכה, halacha, he was so brilliant.
Now it's a little funny because רב נהוראי Rav Nehorai also pretty
much means same same thing. Now we go on anyway in a
similar
way: ולא נהוראי שמו. Ve-lo Nehorai shemo. Now this is no longer
talking about רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir There is somebody who is known
as רב נהוראי. Rav Nehorai. And that person who is known as
רב נהוראי, Rav Nehorai, that wasn't his original name either. אלא רבי
נחמיה שמו, Ela Rebbe Nechemia shemo, ואמרי לה רבי אלעזר בן ערך
שמו. ve-omrei lah Rebbe Elazar ben Arach shemo. But that was רבי
נחמיה Rebbe Nechemia or רבי אלעזר בן ערך. Rebbe Elazar ben Arach.
ולמה נקרא שמו רב נהוראי? Ve-lamah nikra shemo Rav Nehorai? So why
is he called נהוראי? Nehorai? שמנהיר עיני
חכמים בהלכה. She-man-ir einei chachamim ba-halacha. Because he would enlighten the eyes
of the sages. So again נהוראי Nehorai and מאיר Meir are about
the same thing, not exactly clear why they had to change רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir name. But what I think is more interesting is,
excuse me, he would enlighten their eyes בהלכה? ba-halacha? They just said
that nobody understood what he was talking about!
So what it might mean is that he was so brilliant that
he forced them to up their game, you know, in order you
know in order to to try to get what he was saying,
they had to really you know work much harder and he sharpened
their intellect. It doesn't mean that, you know, that in the end
they still couldn't keep up with him, but at least in that
engagement he sharpened their intellect. And it's interesting though, because, you know,
I think there's a very interesting tension that the גמרא's Gemara playing
out, which is on the one hand admitting that you could be
so brilliant you could prove something false to be true, and then
you would say so it's very, very dangerous, that idea, that degree
of intellect. So, but then it's interesting, it immediately says that he
enlightened their eyes בהלכה, ba-halacha, which means that that actually helped them
do better הלכה. halacha. So just because in theory it could be
dangerous, you know, doesn't mean that obviously intellect is a bad thing.
And the fact that he forced them with his argument, you know,
it's sort of like the לחדד בהן את התלמידים le-chadid ba-sa hatalmidim
that we had in the עמוד א, amud alef, even saying opposite
things and force them to, you know, sharpen themselves, ultimately that led
to better הלכה. halacha. Okay, but what it does prove by the
way, and this is always, you know, an issue is how important
of the role of like integrity is in the halachic process because
it's so easy, you know, if you know enough, if you're smart
enough and you know enough sources, you could almost make any type
of a halachic argument. I think we have somebody that once said
something to that effect, right? Where there's a rabbinic will, there's a
halachic way. So the question is, okay, so if you can make
any argument, what defines something as legitimate or not legitimate הלכה? halacha?
And that really is I think the question that's being put on
the table. Obviously to some degree your sense of integrity and what
are you being true to what the sources are really saying is
a question, not just what type of argument in theory could you
make. But again, the contrast that he could make something false true,
but then that by doing that, by demonstrating that, he made everybody
smarter and better at הלכה halacha is I think an important project.
Wait, but doesn't the גמרא Gemara sort of do that all the
time? Like, you know, the גמרא Gemara seems to say something, it's
like yeah but what if we do, oh maybe the גמרא Gemara
really meaning, you know. Yeah, so that's always the question. Exactly that,
that the halachic process is through, you know, reinterpreting and reconciling and
using intellectual acuity to interpret things in ways maybe they didn't originally
mean. So that's the question. Okay, so that's the question. What are
the limits? What are the parameters? You know, is there any end?
Certainly if you come to a conclusion that is actually false, okay,
then obviously doesn't matter how good of a process you went through.
But that's not what he did. He said he was so smart
he could have done it.
Right. Okay. Well, no, he says he did, and not that he
said it להלכה. lehalacha. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay. אמר רבי, said רבי, who was a student of, you know,
of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir he followed רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. in
the פסקנינג paskening of in the in the משנה. Mishnah. האי דמחדדנא
מחבראי, Hai de-mechadedna mechaberai, the fact that I am sharper than my
fellow students—again, here's this idea of intellectual acuity, I'm sharper than them—דחזיתיה
לרבי מאיר מאחוריו. dechazitei le-Rabbi Meir me-achorei.
Because I at least, not only I heard the teaching of רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir I actually was able to see him as he
was teaching. But I only got him from the, I saw him
from the back. I sat behind him. ואילו חזיתיה מקמיה, Ve-ilu chazitei
mikamei,
had I actually been able to see him from in the front,
הוי מחדדנא טפי, havei mechadedna tfei, I would be even smarter, even
sharper. No, literally? Literally.
Wait, but didn't רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir sit in front of the
תלמידים? talmidim? What do you mean?
Maybe they had people sitting all around. It was a crowded room.
How would that affect it?
Well, I'll talk about that in a minute. דכתיב, De-ketiv, as it
says, והיו עיניך רואות את מוריך. Ve-hayu eynecha ro-ot et morecha. Your
eyes should see your teachers. Now, some explain this as, you know,
very
literal, but also like very practically, which is, is that like, you
know, what do they say? 90% of communication is nonverbal? And they
actually say that if you saw the expression on his face, you
saw how he was like winking, how he was, you know, like,
you know, his more of his hand movements and his facial expressions,
you would have gotten greater nuance in what he was actually saying.
So it actually speaks about how much of communication is nonverbal and
I missed something by, I got something by seeing him from the
back, you know, you can still see his body motions and the
way he tilts his head. I don't know, whatever, maybe, you know.
So those types of things, but, you know, if I saw from
the front, I would have even picked up more. That could be
like one way in which it's saying. I think that there's another
thing as well which has to do with the, before you, you
know, with like the passion of the teacher. Like somehow, you know,
somebody gets so excited and passionate, and even if it doesn't give
you a greater nuance in terms of what this means, but that
also is like a spur for you to push yourself even further.
So we spoke about how רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir intellect pushed his
students further, you know, now maybe it's also just his whole general
gestalt and his approach, you know, and being connected to him in
that way would have inspired them even more and pushed them, you
know, even in a greater, even in a greater way. And some
say, you know, obviously some read this more metaphorically even, that somehow,
I don't know, you get their, somehow their divine aura or something.
But I also think that the idea of inspiration, you know, comes
not just again by seeing how somebody acts and is, but sometimes,
you know, you know, if you see a very important person and,
and yeah, like you see, you know, the holiness or the glow
or whatever, you know, that's a, it can be something that really
is very powerful at spurring somebody in terms of their, in terms
of their growth. So I think it could be more than just
the question of the content of the communication in terms of the
importance of that sense of direct engagement with a teacher. Yes.
I'm still reminded of that
story about שבת Shabbat where it was
רבי אלעזר בן
ערך
Rabbi Elazar
ben
Arach who went to that place of, you know, beautiful springs and
whatever and forgot all his תורה. Right, right. Intellect will only get
you so far, you
know.
Right, it's the
engagement
with—right, the
engagement with your
colleagues and with other people. Right, exactly. If you go away with
all your—with all your brilliance, you lose all your
תורה.
Exactly. And I think today with this whole scan— Okay.
That's true. That's another conversation about the difference between and I do
think by the way that that might also be what the גמרא
Gemara is getting at. It held up, you know, I think I
see these two things as a like as a as a counterweight
or a pushback. It held up רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir, as complete
brilliant person that nobody could understand. Like, okay, so what good is
the intellect if you can come up to opposite conclusions? And then
the immediate next two stories is number one actually it made everybody
better in הלכה. halacha. And number two, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, wasn't
just a person of intellect. You know, if he's just a person
of intellect then it's about his brain, but actually the personal engagement
was a very important part of who he was as well. And
it, you know, and it and it it
made a difference to other people and their growing intellectually as well.
Yes.
In academia, these professors who get the best ratings are the professors
who dazzle the students with their brilliance and make things make things
easy to follow, but the students learn better from the professors who
don't make things so crystal clear and force the students to work.
And those professors never get very good ratings.
Very interesting.
Maybe just his אגדות aggadot with משה Moshe that I want to
see God.
Oh, פני לא יראו וראית
את אחורי.
panai lo yeira'u vera'ita
et achorai. Oh, that's very nice. I didn't think about that, but
you're right, that's a direct connection. Right, you can't see my face,
you can see my back. So here רבי saw the back of
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir Very nice. אמרי ואמרי אמר רבי יוחנן, Amre
v'amre amar Rabbi Yochanan, תלמיד היה לו לרבי מאיר. talmid haya lo
l'Rabbi Meir. So we were speaking about רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, being
a student of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל. Now we're
talking about his student. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir had a student
וסומכוס שמו, v'Sumchus shemo, his name was סומכוס, Sumchus, שהיה אומר כל
דבר ודבר של טומאה ארבעים ושמונה טעמי טומאה.
shehaya
omer
kol davar v'davar shel tumah arbaim ushmonah ta'amei tumah. And anything that
was טמא tamei
he gave forty-eight demonstrations why it was טמא. tamei. ועל כל דבר
ודבר של טהרה ארבעים ושמונה טעמי טהרה, v'al kol davar v'davar shel
taharah arbaim ushmonah ta'amei tahara, forty-eight. המהרש"א The Maharsha points out because,
you know, it says that there were fifty gates of wisdom. משה
ותחסרהו מעט מאלהים, Moshe vatasreihu me'at me'elohim, משה Moshe had forty-nine. So
presumably everybody else, the most you could get is one less than
משה. Moshe. So סומכוס Sumchus was just one under משה רבינו. Moshe
Rabbeinu. But again, presumably because he was a student of רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir, and got all of this sharpness from רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir but it's interesting again, again, seeing this in a dialectic what
that first statement of saying on טמא טהור, tamei tahor, that he
might have gotten all this wisdom from רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir. but
he still was using it to prove the right thing, not the
wrong thing. תנא. Now we talk in a ברייתא. תלמיד ותיק היה
ביבנה, Talmid vatik haya b'Yavne,
there was an old תלמיד talmid in יבנה. Yavne. שהיה מטהר את
השרץ במאה וחמישים
טעמים.
Shehaya metaher et hasheretz
b'me'ah vachamishim teamim.
He could give a hundred and fifty ways to prove that a
שרץ sheretz was טהור. tahor. So we're back to this idea about
proving the opposite. But again, notice that it switched from being רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir to now being some anonymous guy. There's some anonymous
guy that could do this. So, you know, downplaying the significance. Again,
I think it's important. It first holds up the brilliance of רבי
מאיר, but immediately has this like corrective. You got other people smarter,
he improved הלכה, halacha, רבי מאיר's student proved טמא tamei was טמא
tamei and טהור tahor was טהור. tahor. And now this idea of
being able to prove the opposite is sort of being ascribed to
some anonymous person. אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, one minute. רבינא Ravina says,
אני אדון ואטהרנו, ani adun v'ataharenu, let
me try my hand at this. I'll make an argument that a
שרץ sheretz should be טהור. tahor. What's the argument? ומה נחש שממית
ומרבה טומאה טהור שרץ שאינו ממית ואינו מרבה טומאה לא כל שכן.
u'mah nachash shemeimit u'marbeh tumah tahor, sheretz she'eino meimit v'eino marbeh tumah
lo kol sheken. A snake which can kill and bring death, it
can kill a person, can kill an animal, and it creates טומאה
tumah in the world, and nevertheless a snake is טהור, tahor, that
snake is טהור. tahor. It's not one of the שמונה שרצים shmonah
shratzim that the תורה said is טמא. tamei. שרץ, Sheretz, one of
these eight rodents
that doesn't kill and bring טומאה tumah to the world, לא כל
שכן, lo kol sheken, certainly should be טהור. tahor. So I've made
an argument too that a שרץ sheretz should be טהור. tahor. Okay?
ולא היא, v'lo hi, and the גמרא Gemara like, psh, that's not
a proof. Like that's not convincing. מעשה קוץ בעלמא
הוא. Ma'aseh kotz b'alma hu. If the snake—it's not like the snake
is intrinsically the source of טומאה. tumah. It's like a thorn, you
know, it sticks
a guy with poison. Now of course, okay, but it still leads
to death and leads to טומאה, tumah, but the גמרא Gemara is
saying yeah, that's not an impressive proof. So it doesn't even count
as one. And this guy had a hundred and fifty. So again,
it's like, it's interesting, the גמרא's Gemara willing to like play the
game, but maybe also by dismissing it, again, what it's trying to
do is to downplay this whole approach. It starts with holding up
רבי מאיר, it has this whole counterbalancing of רבי מאיר about, you
know, how this—you know, about in the positive way, it's not that—and
then when it quotes, it now ascribes it to this anonymous person
and somebody else wants to say, 'Oh, I want to play this
game,' and the גמרא's Gemara response is like a little discouraging. So
I sort of see this whole thing as on the one hand
holding it up as brilliant, but on the other hand very much
moving away from this whole approach about like trying to prove the
opposite. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב
אבא אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Abba amar Shmuel, שלש שנים נחלקו בית
שמאי ובית הלל. shalosh shanim nechleku Beit Shammai u'Veit Hillel. Now we
get to a very famous גמרא Gemara, about בית שמאי Beit Shammai
and בית הלל. Beit Hillel. To some degree it's because we are
talking about, you know, you know, the תנאים and the different approaches,
but I think it also very much plays into the theme we've
been discussing. So, three years בית שמאי Beit Shammai disagreed. הללו אומרים
הלכה כמותנו והללו אומרים הלכה כמותנו. Hallalu omrim halacha k'moseinu v'hallalu omrim
halacha k'moseinu.
They were disagreeing about who the הלכה Halacha should be like. Now
it's no big surprise, everybody would say the הלכה Halacha should be
like me. But if presumably the way the ראשונים Rishonim explain this
is they were actually debating procedural questions, which is, you know, that
בית הלל Beit Hillel was the majority in numbers and בית שמאי
Beit Shammai were the smarter ones. So the question is, do you
rule by, you know, do the ones that are smarter get a
bigger vote? So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says we should be it
should be with us and בית הלל Beit Hillel says it should
be with us. יצאה בת קול ואמרה, Yatza bas kol v'amra, a
heavenly voice came out and said, אלו ואלו דברי אלוהים חיים, Eilu
v'eilu divrei Elokim chayim, these and these are the words of the
living God, הן והלכה כבית הלל, hein v'halacha k'Beit Hillel,
but we rule like בית הלל. Beit Hillel. So the גמרא Gemara
says, וכי מאחר שאלו ואלו דברי אלוהים חיים, v'chi meachar she-eilu v'eilu
divrei Elokim chayim,
if these and these are the words of the living God, מפני
מה זכו בית הלל לקבוע הלכה כמותן, mipnei mah zachu Beit Hillel
likboa halacha k'mosan, why do we go like בית הלל? Beit Hillel?
Now notice it doesn't say if these and these are the living
God, how do we פוסק posken like anyone? Right? That could be
a better question, right? If everyone is true, how do we פוסק?
posken? Because clearly the גמרא Gemara understands that there's a difference between
being a theoretical truth of what the תורה means and that when
you actually פוסק הלכה posken halacha you have to make a decision.
You can't have 50 different ways of living a הלכה'דיק Halachik life.
I mean, we do have ספרדים Sefardim and אשכנזים Ashkenazim and some
difference, but nevertheless there's a practical way in which you have to
rule even if in theory each opinion has legitimacy.
Is this שרץ sheretz really טהור? tahor?
Is this שרץ sheretz as hundred fifty-one... right now, what does אלו
ואלו דברי אלוהים חיים eilu v'eilu divrei Elokim chayim mean? It's very
important, I'll tell you what the ריטב"א Ritva says but it's really
based on the רמב"ם Rambam and it's really based on a general
question about how you think about the whole nature of תורה שבעל
פה. Torah She-be-al Peh. You know, some people think that the nature
of תורה שבעל פה, Torah She-be-al Peh, they base themselves on a
certain אגדתא Agadita in the גמרא, Gemara, is that everything was given
from משה Moshe at סיני, Sinai, all of the specific rulings of
how do we deal with every single question that's ever raised
in the גמרא Gemara and it was all passed on. But if
that's true, then where are the debates coming from? So the debates
come from a problem in
transmission, forgetfulness. Now that's funny because number one is when you read
the גמרא Gemara it does not sound like it's just a question
of transmission, it sounds like people are using their logic to arrive
at positions. You could say, well, what they're trying to do is
they're trying to recapture what was originally told. Fine, but then at
the end of the day, you know, it's still a question about
non-secure transmission. And for רמב"ם, Rambam, this was a very problematic, A
because it gave a big opening for a critique of the קראים,
Kara'im, if you guys have so many debates and you're not having
a legitimate- so you can't trust your transmission, how can we trust
anything? And you know, clearly you don't remember what was taught and
you don't have a legitimate tradition. And number two, it also just
seems not true to what's really going on in the גמרא, Gemara
that it's all just a question of transmission. So the רמב"ם's Rambam
position was the diametrical opposite. He said there's only a very tiny
part of תורה שבעל פה Torah She-be-al Peh which was direct transmission,
the הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai, a handful of teachings. Everything
else, the other 99.9% was all using human creativity and intellect to
interpret the תורה and it was not pre-given by God. There are
rules, there are the, you know, hermeneutical rules, י"ג מידות שהתורה נדרשת
בהן, yud-gimmel middos she-ha-Torah nidreshes bahen, there are ways in which you
have to, you know, interpret, there are parameters, but nevertheless all of
the debates are the application of human intellect
to interpreting the תורה. So that is really the best explanation of
אלו ואלו דברי אלוהים חיים, eilu v'eilu divrei Elokim chayim, and that's
what the ריטב"א Ritva says but he's really getting it from the
רמב"ם, Rambam, which means there's no one meaning of what this פסוק
pasuk means. It's open for interpretation and there are multiple different legitimate
interpretations of what this הלכה halacha of what this פסוק pasuk should
be. And in theory, the הלכה halacha could be like anyone because
it's not that there's one original meaning and if we don't get
that one original meaning we got it wrong. No, there's a text
and it's open for multiple meanings and it's based on how you
as the רבנים rabbanim and as human beings will interpret it. So
if that's true, אלו ואלו דברי אלוהים חיים, eilu v'eilu divrei Elokim
chayim, these are both legitimate interpretations. But we have to rule a
הלכה. halacha. So now the גמרא Gemara says, fine, so what made
us rule like בית הלל? Beit Hillel? ומפני מה זכו בית הלל
לקבוע הלכה כמותן? u-mipnei mah zachu Beit Hillel likboa halacha k'mosan?
So why did בית הלל Beit Hillel merit that the הלכה halacha
was like them? מפני שנוחין ועלובין היו, mipnei she-nochin v'aluvin hayu,
because they were pleasant and they were, you know, what? Modest or
עלוב aluv more sort of means nice? Yeah, like exactly. They didn't
they weren't prideful, you know, they didn't stand on, you know, you
know, they they gave way to other people.
ושונים דבריהם ודברי בית שמאי, v'shonim divreihem v'divrei Beit Shammai, and they
would not only teach their position, they'd even teach the positions of
בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. ולא עוד, v'lo od, and not only this,
אלא שמקדימין דברי בית שמאי לדבריהם, ella she-makdimin divrei Beit Shammai l'divreihem,
they would first mention the position of בית שמאי Beit Shammai before
they mentioned their own position. הכי השתא... Hachi hashta... כאותה ששנינו, k'osah
she-shaninu, like we taught in the משנה: Mishnah: מי שהיה ראשו ורובו
בסוכה ושולחנו בתוך הבית, mi she-hayah rosho v'rubo ba-sukkah v'shulchano b'soch ha-bayis,
somebody whose head and body was in a סוכה sukkah but the
table was inside the house, בית שמאי פוסלין ובית הלל מכשירין, Beit
Shammai poslin u-Beit Hillel machshirin, בית שמאי Beit Shammai says it's not
good and בית הלל Beit Hillel says it's good. אמרו בית הלל
לבית שמאי, amru Beit Hillel l'Beit Shammai, בית הלל Beit Hillel said
to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, לא כך היה מעשה, lo kach hayah
ma'aseh, how could you say this? Wasn't there a story, שהלכו זקני
בית שמאי וזקני בית הלל, she-halchu ziknei Beit Shammai v'ziknei Beit Hillel,
the elders of בית שמאי Beit Shammai and the elders of בית
הלל Beit Hillel went, לבקר את levaker es רבי יוחנן... Rabbi Yochanan...
To visit רבי יוחנן בן החורנית Rabbi Yochanan ben HaChoranis ומצאוהו יושב
ראשו ורובו בסוכה, umtza'uhu yoshev rosho verubo basukkah, they saw him sitting
and he and the majority of his body was in the סוכה,
sukkah, the שולחנו בתוך הבית shulchano betoch habayit and his שולחן shulchan
is in the house, so you see and they didn't say anything?
So you see that it's not a problem and even the elders
of בית שמאי Beis Shammai were there. אמרו להם בית שמאי, Amru
lahem Beis Shammai, בית שמאי Beis Shammai said back to them: משם
ראיה? misham raya? From there you want to bring a proof? אף
הם אמרו לו, Af hem amru lo, they did say something. What
they said to him was אם כך היית נוהג, im kach hayita
noheg, if this is how you've been acting with your table in
the house, לא קיימת מצוות סוכה מימיך, lo kiyamta mitzvat sukkah miyamecha,
then you'd never fulfill the מצווה mitzvah of סוכה. sukkah. So anyway,
bracketing the issue about סוכה, sukkah, you see that they taught the
words of בית שמאי Beis Shammai before them. Now where did they
see that? You could say because when they were telling over the
story, they said the elders of שמאי, Shammai, the elders of הלל,
Hillel, which shows that they afforded respect to שמאי Shammai before הלל.
Hillel. They didn't say the elders of הלל, Hillel, the elders of
שמאי, Shammai, they mentioned שמאי Shammai before. It doesn't exactly direct evidence
that they taught the position of בית שמאי Beis Shammai first, unless
you say that the beginning of that משנה mishnah was also coming
from the teaching of בית הלל. Beis Hillel.
Basically, whenever we teach בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי, Beis
Shammai, we always teach בית שמאי Beis Shammai before בית הלל. Beis
Hillel. So some say that that was רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi following the lead of בית הלל Beis Hillel to teach the
position of שמאי Shammai before the position of הלל. Hillel. So they
were so modest, the הלכה halacha was like them. I'm going to
get back to that. And the גמרא Gemara says ללמדך lelamedcha and
this teaches you שכל המשפיל עצמו, shekol hamashpil atzmo, anybody that lowers
himself, הקדוש ברוך הוא מגביהו, HaKadosh Baruch Hu magbiho, God lifts him
up. וכל המגביה עצמו, Vechol hamagbiya atzmo, and the opposite, if somebody
makes himself high and mighty, הקדוש ברוך הוא משפילו, HaKadosh Baruch Hu
mashpilo, God makes him lowly. כל המחזר אחר הגדולה, Kol hamichazer achar
hagedola, if somebody seeks out greatness, גדולה בורחת
ממנו, gedola borachat mimeno, then greatness runs away from him. וכל הבורח
מן הגדולה, Vechol haborayach min hagedola, anybody that runs away from greatness,
גדולה מחזרת אחריו, gedola mechazeret acharav, greatness runs after him. וכל הדוחק
את השעה, Vechol hadochek et hasha'ah, anybody that presses the hour, which
means like רש"י Rashi says you're trying to get rich or something
and
you don't wait for the right time, you're overly eager at achieving
your
goals,
so שעה דוחקתו, sha'ah dochkato,
the hour pushes you away, meaning you're not going to succeed. וכל
הנדחה מפני שעה, Vechol hanidche mipnei sha'ah,
anybody that allows themselves to be set aside for the hour, doesn't
push things before their time, שעה עומדת לו, sha'ah omedet lo, the
hour stands for him.
So, you know, it's sort of like there are these books, these
like
get-rich-quick books. So it's like, you know, I'll be okay with just
getting rich slowly. I don't need to get rich quick. Exactly.
But everybody hears so much about your get-rich-quick schemes, usually they're going
to fail. Now what is the issue here that we rule like
בית הלל? Beis Hillel? What, so because they were such nice people,
they were such צדיקים, tzadikim, we rule like them? That's how you
go by הלכה? halacha? So some try to say that no, the
whole point here is that
because they did not, were not so taken by themselves, they were
humble and they gave honor to בית שמאי Beis Shammai and they
actually taught בית שמאי's Beis Shammai teaching before them, it means that
they actually gave it due consideration and they actually weighed the position
of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and nevertheless they came to their position,
so that means that they are the ones that are really engaging
with multiple voices, whereas בית שמאי Beis Shammai is just speaking to
themselves. And therefore, even if בית שמאי Beis Shammai is smarter, בית
הלל Beis Hillel is the position that really is the one that
fully sort of engages all of the opinions. And in a way,
well, it doesn't, again, there's not wrong אלו ואלו דברי אלוקים חיים.
elu ve'elu divrei Elokim chayim.
So in a way what this גמרא Gemara is, is I think
it's also again a beautiful counterpart to the starting with רבי מאיר.
You know, if you're all by yourselves you can be brilliant, but
you can also come to conclusions which are not, you know, which
are טמא, tamei, טהור, tahor, and so on and brilliance doesn't do
the whole thing.
And so A, number one, just the fact that we rule like
בית הלל Beis Hillel could be a statement that, you know, in
the end we go by numbers and not by brilliance and that's
an interesting halachic question. Like if I'm coming to פסקן pasken and
ninety percent of the previous rabbis פסקן pasken one way and ten
percent the other but the ten percent are more brilliant than the
ninety, I mean is this a general rule? You know, that's one
question. But more to the point about רבי מאיר is about this
is that it's basically saying again, brilliance is not what it's all
about. And the sense of really sort of hearing all the voices,
engaging all the voices, it's more of a populist approach which ultimately
is the ruling of בית הלל. Beis Hillel. Those that actually not
only represent the majority in numbers, but those that actually engage all
of the opinions, you know, those are the types of positions that
one is the way the ציבור tzibur should be פסקנינג, paskening, even
if it's not the position that comes from the most sort of
brilliant segment. You also can point out the fact that in general
בית הלל Beis Hillel was more ציבור tzibur oriented in general. They
seemed more sensitive to the concerns of the common
man. Again, the גמרא Gemara. isn't exactly saying that,
but that seems to be the point here. Yes.
Isn't it that you're פסקנינג paskening through a בת קול bas kol
though, which you're not supposed to do?
Well again, the גמרא Gemara had that issue
before, בת קול bas kol in the
ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. So but we very much translate it in the בבלי
Bavli translates it as a heavenly voice. But of course the problem
is that if you have a procedural debate there's no way of
saying well that's just the whole idea you don't listen to a
בת קול Bas Kol is because you know how we're supposed to
פסקן, pasken, you know, אחרי רבים להטות. acharei rabbim lehattos. We have
a majority we don't go like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you know
in that whole case with the בת קול Bas Kol by the
oven because we know what the הלכה halakha is. Here the problem
was there was a complete impasse. There was no way to reconcile
it because everybody had a different procedure whether you go by the
majority or whether you go by the smart, you know, the smarter
group. It's like I like telling people that the first one of
the first decisions that the Supreme Court made was, you know, when
the country was starting was that the Supreme Court gets to decide
the meaning of the Constitution. So it's like circular, but okay.
That was the first decision that they made. Anyway, so but but
this is very important in terms of I think this issue about
brilliance versus, you know, what really makes good הלכה. halakha. Look it's
a problem nowadays that you have ראשי ישיבה Rashei Yeshiva פסקן-ing pasken
and they're separate from, you know, they're in their own little world
and people trust ראשי ישיבה. Rashei Yeshiva. Oh my god he's so
much more brilliant than my community rabbi, I'm going to go to
him with all my שאלות. shailos. It's completely unprecedented. And to think
that that's what makes good הלכה halakha is just like the book
knowledge and being, you know, brilliant in a vacuum whereas actually, you
know, the real פוסקים poskim had been the ones that were engaged
in the community and that, you know, and that really sort of
understood the realities of the community and understood what it means to
translate הלכה halakha into real life and dealt with those realities, you
know, and that really is, you know, is is how is how,
you know, obviously it helps to also be brilliant but it's a
brilliance that's more engaged rather than sort of in your own ivory
tower which is exactly I think what the גמרא Gemara is dealing
with of the difference between בית שמאי Beis Shammai בית הלל. Beis
Hillel. Okay let's just end this out. תנו רבנן. Tannu Rabbanan. שתי
שנים ומחצה Shtei shanim vemechtza two and a half years
נחלקו nechelaku בית שמאי Beis Shammai בית הלל. Beis Hillel. There was
a debate בית שמאי Beis Shammai בית הלל. Beis Hillel. Luckily it
was a little bit less than the years about they were debating
who to rule the הלכה halakha like. Okay two and a half
not three years. הללו אומרים Hallalu omerim these say נוח לו לאדם
שלא נברא, noach lo leadam shelo nivra, better that a person should
not have been created יותר משנברא yoser mishenivra more than he was
created. One assumes that that was בית שמאי's Beis Shammai position. והללו
אומרים Vehallalu omerim the others say נוח לו לאדם שנברא noach lo
leadam shenivra יותר משלא נברא, yoser mishelo nivra, no it's better that
a person was created. Presumably that was בית הלל Beis Hillel and
a little more optimistic view about, you know, positive view about about
people and so on. נמנו וגמרו Nimnu vegameru they they came to
a vote and they concluded נוח לו לאדם שלא נברא יותר משנברא
noach lo leadam shelo nivra yoser mishenivra better that a person is
not or should not have been created rather than created. Interesting. So
more pessimistic view of life. But עכשיו שנברא achshav shenivra now that
we are created, you know, על כרחך אתה חי, al korchacha ata
chai, so יפשפש במעשיו yefashpesh bemaasav you should investigate your deeds. ואמרי
לה Veamri lei ימשמש במעשיו yemashmesh bemaasav you should feel your deeds.
Is there a difference? So the difference is some say יפשפש במעשיו
yefashpesh bemaasav means that that before you do something you should give
it a lot of thought how you're going to act. ימשמש במעשיו
Yemashmesh bemaasav could be after you do something you, you know, reflect
on it and what?
רש"י Rashi says the opposite.
Oh I'm sorry רש"י Rashi says the opposite. יפשפש במעשיו Yefashpesh bemaasav
after you've done something you reflect on it and see if you
need to do תשובה teshuva if you could have been done better.
ימשמש במעשיו Yemashmesh bemaasav means before you've done it you think about
what's the right thing to do. The מסילת ישרים Mesillas Yesharim says
the difference is a) making sure you're doing the right thing rather
than the wrong thing and b) even when you're doing the right
thing making sure you're doing it in the best possible way. Anyway
I do want to just end by saying that it is a
little pessimistic. Better not to have been created. You know and what
does that mean? I mean, you know, first פרק perek in בראשית,
Bereishis, וירא אלהים כי טוב, Vayar Elokim ki tov, I mean God
obviously created the world it's good that we were created that humans
were created. So the point here is first of all it's נוח
לו לאדם. noach lo leadam. Maybe in some objective way it's good
that humans are created, but for you personally the likelihood of sin
is greater than that of merit. So for you personally it might
have been better not to. The others say the the key is
the word נוח. noach. Doesn't mean טוב. tov. It might be טוב
tov that you were created, but נוח noach means is it pleasant?
Is it the types of challenges is it an easy life or
a non-easy life particularly in the sense of a life that you
have to keep on the straight and narrow. It is quite fascinating
that in the end they ended with the more pessimistic position given
that that seems much more of a בית שמאי Beis Shammai view
than a בית הלל Beis Hillel view. Yes.
Well I mean that brings up an interesting question. Why do we
ever convert anybody if it's easier to keep the Noachide? And there's
no way that a convert's not...
Yeah so this is this is not a גמרא. The previous גמרא
is quoted very much about why we rule like בית הלל Beis
Hillel not בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. Not too many people quote this
גמרא of נוח לו לאדם שלא נברא. noach lo leadam shelo nivra.
Very pessimistic view on life in general. Okay for more tomorrow.